Ali Zain

Bio

My research is focused on misinformation, new media, strategic communication, and bigdata analytics. I use traditional qualitative and quantitative methods as well as computational and psycho-physiological methods. Moreover, I have experience of teaching courses in the areas of advertising, public relations, and mass communication. I have received USC Breakthrough Graduate Scholar Award, CHQ Junior Scholar Award, top paper awards by the AEJMC and the AEJMCSEC, and travel grants by the ICA and the AEJMC.

EDUCATION

2020 -

SMC '23

	University of South Carolina, Columbia (USC)			
– Present	Ph.D. Candidate - All But Dissertation (ABD)			Ph.D. in Mass Communication
			_	1 0 - 1 0

Dissertation Topic: Using Information Processing Approach to Counter Spread of Online Misinformation

Dissertation Committee: Drs. Sei-Hill Kim (Chair), Jungmi Jun, Taylor Wen, and Amir Karami

2018 – 2020 Hacettepe University, Ankara (HU) M.A. IN COMMUNICATION SCIENCES
2011 – 2015 University of the Punjab, Lahore (PU) B.S. IN COMMUNICATION STUDIES

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2020 – Present	University of South Carolina (USC)	Graduate Research Assistant/Instructor of Record
2023 – Present	USC Biometrics and User Experience Lab (BaUX)	Graduate Assistant
2016 – 2017	Al-Khidmat Foundation Pakistan (AKFP)	Digital Media Strategist
2014 – 2016	Daily Pakistan (DP)	Content Editor

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

FA '23	JOUR 331 – Social Media Marketing Strategy	Instructor of Record
SP '21 '23, FA '22	JOUR 332 – Mass Communications Research	Teaching Assistant
SP '23	JOUR 542 – Public Opinion and Persuasion	Teaching Assistant
SP '23	JOUR 715 – Strategic Communications Strategies	Teaching Assistant
SP '23	JOUR 772 – Health, Science and the Media	Teaching Assistant
FA '22	JOUR 705 – Strategic Communication Principles	Teaching Assistant
FA '22	JOUR 536 – Crisis Communication	Teaching Assistant
FA '21, SP 22	JOUR 220 – Account Planning: Mining Insights	Instructor of Record
FA '20 '21, SP '22	JOUR 533 – Public Relations Management	Teaching Assistant
FA '20 '21	JOUR 507 – Communicating Science, Health and the Environment	Teaching Assistant

PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Zain, A. and Ciccarelli, C. (In Press). Political partisanship and belief in misinformation: operationalizing theory of planned behavior to predict intentions to quit social media. *Southwestern Mass Communication Journal*

JoHC '23	Ittefaq, M., Zain, A., and Bokhari, H. (2023). Opioids as comedy: exploring topics, sentiments, and engagement in Last Week Tonight with John Oliver on YouTube. <i>Journal of Health Communication</i> . https://doi.org/10.1080/10810730.2023.2176575
PUS '23	Chen, Y., Long, J., Jun. J., Kim, S., Zain, A., and Piacentine, C. (2023). Anti-intellectualism amid the covid-19 pandemic: the dynamics of anti-Fauci discourse on Twitter. <i>Public Understanding of Science</i> . https://doi.org/10.1177/09636625221146269
ЈоНС '23	Jun. J., Wickersham, K., Zain, A., Ford, R., Zhang, N., Ciccarelli, C., Kim, S., and Liang, C. (2023). Cancer and COVID-19 Vaccines on Twitter: The Voice and Vaccine Attitude of Cancer Community. <i>Journal of Health Communication</i> . https://doi.org/10.1080/10810730.2023.2168800
SCJ '23	Zain, A. (2023). Celebrity capital and social movements: a textual analysis of Bollywood celebrities' tweets on 2020-21 Indian farmers' protest. Southern Communication Journal. https://doi.org/10.1080/1041794X.2022.2160006
AJHB '22	Jun, J., Fitzpatrick, MA., <u>Zain, A.</u> , and Zhang, N. (2022). Have e-cigarette risk perception and cessation intent of young adult users changed during the pandemic? <i>American Journal of Health Behaviors</i> , 46 (3), 304-314(11). https://doi.org/10.5993/AJHB.46.3.9
VACCINES '22	Jun, J., Zain, A., Chen, Y., and Kim, S. H. (2022). Adverse mentions, negative sentiment, and emotions in covid-19 vaccine tweets and their association with vaccination uptake: global comparison of 192 countries. <i>Vaccines</i> , 10(5), 735. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines10050735
Etkileşim '22	Dino Gidreta, A., Binark, M., Ozsu, G. and Zain, A. (2022). Trusts and doubts in Africa over Belt and Road Initiative: a thematic content analysis of opinions in Ethiopian twittersphere. <i>Etkileşim</i> 5(9), 12-35. DOI: 10.32739/etkilesim.2022.5.9.153
SU&M '22	Jun, J., Zhang, N., Zain, A. and Mohammadi, E. (2022). Social media discussions on the FDA's modified risk tobacco product authorization of IQOS. Substance Use and Misuse 57(3), 472-480. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2021.2019777
JAS '21	Zain, A. (2021). (Re)Production of hindutva-driven populism in India: an analysis of Bharatiya Janata Party's political messaging in twittersphere. <i>The Journal of Asian Studies</i> 5(2), 179-194. DOI: 10.34189/asyam.5.2.005
JAS '20	Zain, A., Ozsu, G., Binark, M. and Dino Gidreta, A. (2020). China-Pakistan Economic Corridor and technicians of opinion in Pakistani twittersphere: a thematic content analysis. <i>The Journal of Asian Studies</i> 4(1),9-28. DOI: 10.34189/asyam.4.1.002
MOMENT '19	Zain, A. (2019). Rise of Modi's tech-populism in India. <i>Moment Journal</i> 6(1),199-208. DOI: 10.17572/mj2019.1.199208
	PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS
AEJMC '23	Zain, A., Li, Z., Liang, C., and Li, X. (2023, August). Diffusion of polarized information on Twitter and vaccination behaviors: Understanding intertwined role of moralization and emotions. 106th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Washington DC.
AEJMC '23	Jun, J., Wen, J., Zain, A., and Alharbi, K. (2023, August). The Influence of 'US FDA' Authorized Modified Exposure Claim on Heuristic Processing of Warnings, Positive Evaluation, and Greater Acceptance of Novel Tobacco Promotional Message Among Young Adults. 106th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Washington DC.
ICA '23	Bhala, N., <u>Zain, A.</u> , and O'Boyle, J. (2023, May). Twitter Conversations about Causes, Solutions and Effects of Delhi Air Pollution: Agenda-Building Content Analysis. 73rd Annual International Communication Association Conference. Toronto, Canada.

Zain, A. (2022, August). Moralization in polarized debate on COVID-19 vaccination: human-AI collaborative analysis of AEJMC '22 tweets. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, MI. First Place Moeller Student Paper Award Zain, A. and Long, J. (2022, August). Countering online misinformation: testing impact of state sponsorship labels on message credibility, verification intention and behavior. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass AEJMC '22 Communication Conference, Detroit, MI. Zain, A. (2022, August). Spiral of silence 50 years later: conceptual and empirical new directions. 105th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, Detroit, MI. AEJMC '22 Ittefaq, M., Zain, A., and Bokhari, H. (2022, May). Opioids as comedy: exploring topics, sentiments, and engagement in Last Week Tonight with John Oliver on YouTube. 72nd Annual International Communication Association Conference. Paris, France. ICA '22 Chen, Y., Long, J., Jun, J., Kim, S., Zain, A., and Piacentine, C. (2022, May). Anti-intellectualism amid the covid-19 pandemic: the dynamics of anti-Fauci discourse on Twitter. 72nd Annual International Communication Association Conference. Paris, France. ICA '22 Zain, A. (2022, March). Online endorsed misinformation and climate change: using heuristic cues to assess perceived AEJMCSEC '22 credibility of messages and sharing intentions. 47th Annual AEJMC Southeast Colloquium, Memphis, TN. Top Student Paper Award Jun, J. and Zain, A. (2022, February). Global comparison of covid-19 vaccination sentiments and emotions on Twitter: findings from 192 countries. 3rd National Big Data Health Sciences Conference. Columbia, SC BDHS '22 Zain, A. (2021, August). Using theory of planned behavior, and operationalization of political partisanship and belief in misinformation to predict individuals' intentions to quit social media. 104th Annual Association for Education in AEJMC '21 Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA. Jun, J., Fitzpatrick, MA., Zhang, N., and Zain, A. (2021, August). Has covid-19 impacted the risk perceptions and cessation intent of youth vapers? 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication AEJMC '21 Conference, New Orleans, LA. Zain, A. (2021, August). Celebrity capital and social movements: a textual analysis of Bollywood celebrities' tweets on 2020-21 Indian farmers' protest. 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA. AEJMC '21 Kim, S.,Zain, A., and Heo, Y. (2021, August). Idealized science vs. scientific skepticism in South Korea: micro-level evidence for the two-cultures thesis. 104th Annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication Conference, New Orleans, LA. AEJMC '21 Zain, A. (2021, February). Doctrine of hindutva and political discourse of India's Bharatiya Janata Party: an analysis of 2019 election campaign. 1st International Social Sciences Conference, Ankara, Turkey. UBSK'21 Ozsu, G., Zain, A., Binark, M. and Dino Gidreta, A. (2020, November). Technicians of opinion in Ethiopia, Pakistan, and Turkey and their tweets about Chinese vision of alternative globalization: a comparative content analysis. 17th International Symposium: Communication in the Millennium, Istanbul, Turkey. ISBN: 978-605-83703-9-5 CIM '20 Zain, A. (2019, November). Aging-friendly smartphones: analysis of smartphones user-interface to assess their usability among elderly citizens. Senex: 3rd Congress of Aging Studies for Graduate Students, Antalya, Turkey. **SENEX '19** Zain, A. and Soomro, A (2016, November). Cultural continuity and mass media: an analysis of leading online newspapers of Pakistan. 1st National Conference Emerging Trends and Challenges in Social Sciences, Multan, Pakistan. ETCSS'16

BOOKS & BOOK CHAPTERS

Zain, A. (2020). Contact and sanction: cricket as a diplomatic tool in India and Pakistan. In M. Binark (Ed.), Popular culture and media in Asia (pp. 411-440). um:ag Publications.ISBN: 978-605-7882-42-4 2020 Zain, A. (2020). Aging friendly smartphones. In Y. Dede and M. Figan (Ed.), Aging in digital culture and afterwards (pp. 297-314). Alternatif Bilisim Dernegi.ISBN: 978-605-80007-2-8 2020 Zain, A. and Khan, N. T. (2016). Muasharti Jamhooriat. Kettering Foundation. An Urdu translation of The Ecology of Democracy by David Mathews 2016 Under Review Publications Jun, J., Zain, A., Kim, M., Alharbi, K., Kim, J., Ford, R., and Thrasher, J. (Under Review). Young Adults' Responses to the World's Largest Tobacco Company's Promise for Smoke-Free Future: Qualitative Analysis from the Corporate Social Responsibility Communication Perspective 2023 Kim, M., Jun, J., Zain, A., Kim, J., Alharbi, K., and Thrasher, J. (Under Review). Young adults' responses to Philip Morris International's Message Promoting "Smokefree" Product 2023 Kim, S., Oh, S., Zain, A., Heo, Y., and Jun, J. (Under Review: R&R). Idealized Science vs. Culture of Skepticism in South Korea: Micro-Level Evidence for the Two-Culture Model of Public Understanding of Science 2022 Zain, A. and Long, J. (Under Review). Countering State-Sponsored Misinformation: Testing the Effect of Social Media Labels on Message Credibility and Verification. 2022 **IN-PROGRESS PROJECTS** 2022-2023 Countering online misinformation: a mixed methods approach to assess efficacy of social media labels. Cancer communication ecologies of minority populations in the United States. 2023 Identifying Optimal Visual Narratives to Impact African American Men's Colorectal Cancer Risk Awareness and Screening Uptake. 2023 Telehealth use during the pandemic: social determinants and associated health outcomes among the US population. 2023 This ad speaks to me: an investigation of mechanisms underlying social identity relevant advertising. 2022-23 A systematic review of COVID-19 false information studies. 2022-23 Analyzing tobacco promotion and prevention communities on internet: identifying key players, topics, and entities. 2023 Awards & Honors Breakthrough Graduate Scholar Award: For demonstrating phenomenal commitment to research and scholarly 2023 activity in doctoral studies at USC

First Place Moeller Student Paper Award: For presenting "Moralization in Polarized Debate on COVID-19 Vaccination: Human-AI Collaborative Analysis of Tweets" at 105th annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) conference (including 250 USD cash prize and waiver of conference registration fee worth 200 USD) 2022 Top Student Paper Award: For presenting "Online endorsed misinformation and climate change: using heuristic cues to assess perceived credibility of messages and sharing intentions" at 47th annual conference of AEJMC Southeast Colloquium 2022 University Gold Medal: For securing highest CGPA in BS Communication Studies in the class of 2015 2016 GRANTS & SCHOLARSHIPS Mary Caldwell Graduate Scholarship: Graduate scholarship worth 9,000 USD for the doctoral program at University of South Carolina 2020 - 2023Junior Scholar Award: Training and research support worth 4, 500 USD awarded by South Carolina SmartState Center of Health Quality (CHQ) 2022 -2023USC Graduate School Travel Grant: To attend 73rd Annual International Communication Association Conference in Toronto, Canada. (800 USD) 2023 USC Graduate School Travel Grant: To attend 105th annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) Conference in Detroit, MI (500 USD) 2022 Mass Communication and Society Travel Grant: To attend 105th annual Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) Conference in Detroit, MI (1,000 USD) 2022 ICA 2022 Michael Haley Travel Grant: To attend 72nd International Communication Association Conference in Paris, France (400 USD) 2022 ICA 2022 Political Communication Division Travel Grant: To attend 72nd International Communication Association Conference in Paris, France (400 USD) 2022 Research Grant by Hacettepe University: For the transnational study of China's Belt and Road Initiative (3, 200 2019-2020 Turkiye Graduate Scholarship: Fully funded scholarship for MA in Communication Sciences at Hacettepe 2017-2020 University PU Merit Scholarship: Awarded to 5 top-ranked students at University of the Punjab 2012-2015 PROFESSIONAL TRAINING & CERTIFICATIONS CHQ Junior Scholar Program: Extensive research traineeship offered by the SC SmartState Center for Health 2022 - 2023Quality to apply computational methods for research at the interaction of public health and social media Publication Process & Peer Review Training: Certificate program offered by the Journal of Mass Communication 2022 - 2023Quarterly (JMCQ) focused on formal manuscript review process training Intercultural Inclusion and Diversity Learning Series: A series of training workshops, lectures, and activities focused on diversity, equity, inclusion, and accessibility 2022 SHARPGrads Certificate: The Skills, Habits, and Research Program for Graduate Students offered by the UofSC Digital Research Services and Research Computing Institute focused on training workshops on computing, textual analysis, programming, and visualization tools 2022 Programming for Everybody: online Coursera program offered by University of Michigan focused on python 2021 programming

Citi Certificate on Human Research: Training demonstration program for social and behavioral researchers

offered by Citi Program

2021

2021

2021

HubSpot Social Media Maarketing: Certificate program offered by the HubSpot Academy focused on social media monitoring, content strategy, social engagement, creating social media policies, and demonstrating social ROI Google Analytics: Certificate program offered by the Google Analytics Academy focused on training demonstrations and activities to test online analytical skills

RESEARCH SKILLS

- R/RStats
 BrandWatch
 NodeXL
 Deedose
- Python
 NVivo
 Advanced Excel
 SAS
- iMotions
 Qualtrics
 SEO
 Gephi

TALKS/GUEST LECTURES/MEDIA

2023	Leveraging AI in Advertising	Nor	THERN ARIZONA UNIVERSITY
2023	Using Social Media Analytics in Health Communication	Central Con	NECTICUT STATE UNIVERSITY
2023	Social Media Analytics in Public Relations		SUNY Oswego
2023	Media Writing and Internet		JOHN CARROLL UNIVERSITY
2023	Using Information Processing Perspective to Counter Online Misinfor	mation BS	SU, JCU, SUNY, TAMU, NAU
	Countries with lower-than-expected vaccination rates show unusually attitudes to vaccines on Twitter	negative	
2022	shorturl.at/cHMY5		The Conversation
2021	Use of new media technologies by populist right-wing political parties	in India	HACETTEPE UNIVERSITY
2019	Ageing-friendly smartphones to overcome digital divide in aging socie	ies	Akdeniz University
2017	Journalistic prospects of new media technologies		University of the Punjab

SERVICE TO THE FIELD

2022-2023	Research & Scholarship Advisory Council (USC CIC)	Member
2022-2023		
2023	Journal of Computational Social Science (CSS)	Peer Reviewer
2023	Public Understanding of Science (PUS)	Peer Reviewer
2023	Political Communication Division, International Communication Association (ICA)	Panel Moderator
	Graduate Student Interest Group, Association for Education in Journalism and Mass	
2022-23	Communication (AEJMC)	Peer Reviewer
2021-23	Computational Communication Division, International Communication Association (ICA)	Peer Reviewer
2022	Health Communication Division, International Communication Association (ICA)	Peer Reviewer
2022	Journalism Studies Division, International Communication Association (ICA)	Peer Reviewer
2022	Communication and Technology Division, International Communication Association (ICA)	Peer Reviewer
2022	New Media & Society (NM+S)	Peer Reviewer
2022	Social Media & Society (SM+S)	Peer Reviewer
2022	JMIR Medical Informatics (JMI)	Peer Reviewer
2022	Journal of Social Sciences (JSS)	Peer Reviewer
2022	JMIR Formative Research (JFR)	Peer Reviewer

PEER REVIEWER

2022

REFERENCES

Sei-Hill Kim KIM96@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Eleanor M. & R. Frank Mundy Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-777-7037

Jungmi Jun JUNJ@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Associate Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-576-5982

Mary Anne Fitzpatrick FITZPATM@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Educational Foundation Distinguished Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-777-4614

Taylor Jing Wen JWEN2@MAILBOX.SC.EDU

Associate Professor School of Journalism and Mass Communication University of South Carolina 803-777-3312